Finding aid to the Grace Hazard Conkling Papers CA.MS.00046
Smith College Archives
Grace Hazard Conkling Papers
1887-1992
Smith College Archives
Conkling, Grace Hazard, 1878-1958
CA.MS.00046
1.25 linear feet (4 containers)
2.917 linear feet (5 containers)
Professor of English, poet. Contains biographical information, correspondence, and publications.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Biographical / Historical
Grace Hazard was born on February 7, 1878 in New York to Christopher Grant Hazard and Frances Post Hazard. Having cultivated a skill and love for music from a young age, Conkling dreamed of devoting her life to music. After receiving a B.L. from Smith College in 1899, she spent a year teaching at the Graham School in New York before traveling to Europe where she studied music and languages in Germany and France, studying the organ with the illustrious Charles-Marie Widor. However, in her second year she fell ill from overwork and was forced to abandon the idea of music as a profession. She returned to the United States where she married Roscoe Platt Conkling in 1905 and moved to a remote ranch near Tampico, Mexico. Conkling cherished the time she spent there and Mexico is referred to in many of her poems.
After the birth of her second child, her husband deserted her and the children, and in 1914 she sued for divorce and accepted a teaching position at Smith College. It has been said that being a member of the Smith faculty was good for her creative side because Conkling soon became a very accomplished poet and had numerous books published by the time she retired in 1947.
Conkling's poetry and enthusiasm for teaching was recognized both by Smith and others in the academic community. Her poetry and short stories were published in numerous magazines including the Yale Review, Atlantic Monthly, and Harper's. She was also a member of the Poetry Society of America, the N.E. Poetry Society, the Author's Club of Boston, and the Women's University Club of New York. In 1930, Conkling was awarded an honorary MA from Smith College. She died on November 15, 1958 and was survived by her two daughters and three grandchildren.
Related Material
Class of 1899 Records
Scope and Contents
The papers contain biographical information, correspondence, and publications by and about Grace Hazard Conkling.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Smith College -- History -- Sources; Conkling, Grace Hazard, 1878-1958
- General, 1918-1992 (Box 727)
- Degrees, 1930 (Box 727)
- English Courses, undated (Box 727)
- Speeches and Lectures, 1924-1933 (Box 727)
- Roscoe Platt Conkling, 1926 (Box 727)
- "Mrs. Conkling's 'Junior' Year Abroad, undated (Box 727)
- Heidelberg University, 1903 (Box 727)
- Obituary & Memorial Service, 1958 (Box 727)
- Poetry Society of America, 1915-1930 (Box 727)
- Programs & Invitations, 1903; undated (Box 727)
- Recommendations, 1918 (Box 727)
- Retirement, 1946 (Box 727)
- Score for Organ-original, undated (Box 727)
- Summer Schools, 1929 (Box 727)
- Photographs, undated (Box 727)
- Hilda Conkling (2 files), undated (Box 727)
- Correspondence (Box 728)
  - Abbott, Senda (Berenson), 1929 (Box 728)
  - Abbott, Jere, 1936; 1948 (Box 728)
  - Andrews, J.W., 1905 (Box 728)
  - Arvin, Newton, 1924 (Box 728)
  - Barnard, Frances Fenton, 1925 (Box 728)
  - Blake, Helen P., undated (Box 728)
  - Blodgett, Benjamin, 1899-1915 (Box 728)
  - Burton, Marion L., 1914 (Box 728)
  - Chase, Mary Ellen, 1945 (Box 728)
  - Churchill, Alfred, 1926; 1937 (Box 728)
  - Clark, Annetta I., 1945 (Box 728)
  - Conkling, Grace H., 1905; 1907; 1922; 1951; 1957 (Box 728)
  - Conkling, Grace H (to Sallie Simons), 1940; 1955-1958 (Box 728)
  - Dodd, Marion E., 1923; 1926; 1928; undated (Box 728)
  - Dunn, Esther Cloudman, 1923 (Box 728)
  - Eliot, Ethel Cook, 1945 (Box 728)
  - Faulkner, Mary Waldron, 1924 (Box 728)
  - Filsinger, Sara Teasdale, 1916 (Box 728)
  - Fischer, Alfred Young, undated (Box 728)
  - Ford, Harriet Bliss, 1900-1930 (Box 728)
  - Frazier, Katharine, 1924 (Box 728)
  - Galt, Clarace Eaton, 1923 (Box 728)
  - Gray, Agnes Kendrick, undated (Box 728)
  - Gray, William Dodge, undated (Box 728)
  - Hanscom, Elizabeth D., 1925 (Box 728)
  - Hocking, William, 1903 (Box 728)
  - Hoyt, Helen, undated (Box 728)
  - Loller, Fanny S, 1900-1905; 1917 (Box 728)
  - McAffee, Helen, 1924 (Box 728)
  - McCallum, George B., 1925 (Box 728)
  - MacCracken, Henry N., 1914 (Box 728)
  - MacDowell, M., 1926 (Box 728)
  - Morrow, Elizabeth Cutter, 1926 (Box 728)
  - Nebel, Charlotte, undated (Box 728)
  - Newton, Charoline, 1904 (Box 728)
  - Nicolson, Marjorie, undated (Box 728)
  - Patch, Howard Rollin, 1930 (Box 728)
  - Schinz, Albert, 1922 (Box 728)
  - Peopold, Florence H., undated (Box 728)
  - Phelps, Ruth Shepard, 1934 (Box 728)
  - Sleeper, Henry D., 1905 (Box 728)
  - Swett, Margery, 1924 (Box 728)
  - Vorenkamp, Alphons, 1932; undated (Box 728)
  - Whicher, Harriet F., 1934 (Box 728)
  - Wilder, Charlotte, c1932 (Box 728)
  - Wolfrum, Philipp, 1903 (Box 728)
  - Wolfrum, Regina, undated (Box 728)
  - Wooley, Mary, undated (Box 728)
- Correspondence Home, 1889-1901 (Box 728.1)
- Publications (Box 729)
  - General (Box 729)
  - After Sunset (Box 729)
  - Afternoons of April, 1915 (Box 729)
  - Autumn Campus, undated (Box 729)
  - A Beethoven Andante, undated (Box 729)
  - Connecticut River-Early March, undated (Box 729)
  - Corner of Massachusetts-Early Summer, undated (Box 729)
  - Faculty Meeting, undated (Box 729)
  - February Concert-Country Town, undated (Box 729)
  - Flying Fish: A book of songs and sonnets, 1926 (Box 729)
  - The Fountain, The Hermit Thrust, To Hilda and her Roses, undated (Box 729)
  - Golden Roses, undated (Box 729)
  - His Letter, undated (Box 729)
  - Imagination and Children's Reading, 1922; 1928 (Box 729)
  - Mallorca: November Hurricane, 1928 (Box 729)
  - Mexico, undated (Box 729)
  - Music School Beside a River, undated (Box 729)
  - Nightingales of Flanders (Box 729)
  - Postwar Planning, 1946 Mar (Box 729)
  - Retort Courteous, undated (Box 729)
  - Rhymed Review, c1920 (Box 729)
  - BookScorpion-reviews, 1923 (Box 729)
  - Studies in Modern Languages, 1938 (Box 729)
  - Ship's Log, 1924 (Box 729)
  - The Tree of Starlings, 1965 (Box 729)
  - Tree for Music, 1928 (Box 729)
  - Wilderness Songs, 1920 (Box 729)
  - Witch and Other Poems, 1929 (Box 729)
  - Poems, various, undated (Box 729)
  - Scrapbook of Early Writings, 1887-1905 (Box 729)
- Oversize materials (Box 729.1)